"Why I Changed My Mind on Water Fluoridation"
Community water fluoridation
recently hit
its 75th anniversary,
touted as a significant
advancement in public health,
but new research
suggests the potential
for adverse health impacts.
There's little question
that supplemental fluoride
strengthens teeth
and reduces decay.
But at what cost?
Most of the older studies
were snapshot-in-time studies,
looking only at group-level data
or were based on
higher-than-normal exposure.
That has since changed
with the publication
of prospective studies
following individual
exposure levels from
mother-child pairs over time.
The first few were from Mexico
and correlated
higher fluoride levels
in the urine of pregnant women
with future developmental delay
in their infants.
They found worse cognitive
performance at age four
and lower IQ
from ages six through 12,
but the fluoride was
from fluoridated salt
or water sources where fluoride
was present naturally.
Then, this study
came out of Canada,
the first prospective study
using individual exposure data
dealing directly with
community water fluoridation
receiving quote-unquote
"optimally fluoridated" water.
None of the municipal
water fluoride levels
exceeded 1.5 parts per million,
and the vast majority,
over 90 percent,
were under the U.S.
target of point seven.
Despite drinking
"optimally fluoridated water,"
the study of more than
500 mother-child pairs
found that higher fluoride
exposure during pregnancy,
once again,
appeared to translate
into lower child intelligence,
measured at ages three to four.
The American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists
recommends pregnant women drink
at least eight cups
of water a day.
Based on the Canadian study,
following this advice
with water at U.S.
target fluoridation levels
might result in as much as
a 5-point loss in IQ.
The Canadian study was published
in the American
Medical Association's
pediatrics journal,
the longest running pediatrics
journal in the country.
The editor-in-chief defended its
decision to publish the study
"as testament to the fact that
JAMA Pediatrics is committed
to disseminating
the best science...
regardless of how contentious
the results may be."
The Canadian Agency
for Drugs and Technologies
in Health
issued a rapid response report,
concluding that there
is insufficient evidence
to conclusively conclude
that fluoride exposure
at optimum levels affects
neurological development,
but that's not what
the Canadian study was saying.
The researchers just suggested
the "possible need"
to reduce fluoride intake
during pregnancy.
As the accompanying
editorial concluded,
based on the new data,
"a dispassionate
and tempered discussion
of fluoride's potential
neurotoxicity is warranted."
What was the response
from US regulators?
Within a month of
the Canadian study's release,
the National Toxicology Program,
which is part
of the US Department
of Health and Human Services
that evaluates substances
for potentially harmful
human health effects,
released a draft evaluation
of fluoride exposure
and neurodevelopmental
and cognitive health effects
and concluded that,
"Based on a systematic review
of the evidence,
the NTP concludes that
fluoride is presumed to be
a cognitive neurodevelopmental
hazard to humans."
So we've gone
from dismissing people
who questioned the safety
of water fluoridation
as zealots
or anti-science fanatics,
to the official US National
Toxicology Program saying
we should presume
it's hazardous.
Now, this was just
a draft report.
To ensure the integrity
of its report,
the NTP asked
the National Academies,
probably our most prestigious
scientific institution,
to review it.
The review raised
a bunch of concerns,
which was portrayed
in the dental literature
as "discrediting"
the IQ research.
But that's not what
the National Academies said.
They explicitly said that
their misgivings don't mean
that the NTP conclusion
that fluoride should be presumed
to be neurotoxic is incorrect;
they just wanted
some further analysis.
So, in 2020,
they redrafted their draft,
and once again came
to the same conclusion,
presuming it's a cognitive
neurodevelopmental hazard
based on the extent,
consistency,
and robustness of the IQ data.
The National Academies
then rereviewed
their redrafted draft,
concluding it's much improved,
but urged the NTP
to further improve
the clarity of the document,
and we await
the final NTP report.